in the call that our topic is about how
people consume news and how do they
tackle different perspectives and,
you know, some topics around that. Okay,
so the way we'll go about it is I'll ask
you if you, it'll be a Q&
A sort of discussion and
Towards the end,
I will also show you something that,
you know,
a very basic prototype that we have
created. Actually, Diya has created it,
so that you can also provide some point
of view or if you have any thoughts or
ideas on top of that.
Okay.
Hello?
I speaking on mute. Yeah, yeah,
sounds good. Yeah, let's start.
Yeah.
Okay, sounds good. Okay, great.
So let me start with some
some basic questions.
So how do you typically stay informed
about current events? You know,
what is your daily routine around,
you know, getting information about,
you know,
things that are happening in the world,
etc.?
So 2 primary ways of consuming news.
One is Google News.
I have downloaded the app. So that's the,
like one of the first things I do is I
just cheque the news and that's a habit
earlier. I have to read the paper.
But now Google News has replaced that.
And on Instagram, I follow a few channels,
a few accounts. So I like, again,
related to say tech or like no AI,
there are like some channels that I
follow. So I get to know from that.
And 3rd is on Reddit.
So I like get some of my global news from
Reddit. So yeah,
Mm.
so Google News is mostly like Indian,
India focus news and Instagram and Reddit
is more global.
Okay,
and any specific sources that you rely a
lot or I mean,
you don't have to name the sources.
I mean, it depends on if you want to,
but do you have like specific news
channels or influencers, et cetera,
that you go to for sort of getting a
point of view or just taking news from
there rather than, you know?
Or other sources.
So, well...
Funnily,
nowadays I am not like really looking at
the news outlet.
And especially if I'm going through
Google News,
I'm just reading them as articles.
Mm.
I don't really even see or I can't
register that is this from a specific
news channel.
And I think Google also has built an
algorithm where it would philtre out some
Okay.
of the news outlets,
which I don't want to follow,
like for example,
Republic TV and all of that.
I try not to really follow what they are
talking about because a lot of those news
Hmm.
is...
I find it a waste of my time.
And in terms of Instagram, again,
Hmm.
I don't follow any specific creators.
But these are like very headlines, right?
Hmm.
These are like things that I just want to
like quickly read about.
And it's not a very deep dive.
on specific topics. But there are,
YouTube is a good place where if you want
more detailed analysis.
I have a few channels, I don't remember.
There's one Indian channel,
I think Shekhar Gupta,
you must have heard of.
Yeah, print.
So cut the to cut the clutter is one that
I follow where they talk about a lot of
things in detail.
Then there is also the newsprint and
Hmm.
there is one more I don't remember the
name. Again, that's on Instagram.
But they write very detailed analysis of
certain things which are happening in
India. So be it like the,
and these are things that you don't
really get to read in mainstream media,
but like they do very detailed analysis
of certain topics.
Maybe it is mining in Goa or if it's like
the water project which is happening in
Madhumanti Pradesh and also it.
like goes in deep dives into it and it's
a very detailed report so that I find
helpful. For global news again,
like there are a couple of channels I
follow so I get to know about say I'm
interested in like geopolitics or a lot
of like you know what's happening with
respect to the Ukraine war or.
Mm.
in the Middle East right now with the
Iran and US conflict.
So those things I have certain channels
and they get into like, you know,
more deep dive, explain what is happening.
So.
Okay.
So yeah, at a very high level,
it's Google News and Instagram and Reddit.
And if I have to deep dive,
then I would read about it on specific
platforms or on YouTube.
Okay,
and your medium must be generally phone,
right? Or is it like,
do you use your desktop or?
For to view these videos, it is my TV.
I actually have not used my laptop to
read news in a long time.
So phone and TV are those my 2 mediums.
Okay, fine. Okay,
so moving on to the understanding the
perspective piece, right?
So have you ever read about the same
story from two different sources and
noticed that, you know, they were,
they are told very differently?
And if you have had this, you know,
if you have felt that...
What has your experience been?
In my current experience,
I have not done that.
Like during the student movement,
I did see that no basis like your feed
and this is the kind of content you see,
you are going to see different kind of
reels.
So there were like people talking for and
Mhm.
against.
the movement.
So that is one example that I can think
of. But when I'm consuming news,
I'm mostly now consuming it to just keep
myself updated on what is happening.
So I'm not gotten very deep into the
topic.
So I try to find a neutral,
I try to find some neutral channels,
not channels,
neutral mediums where they are more,
they're not leaning on either side of the
political spectrum.
So I try to limit myself from that.
Mm.
Like,
but I'm not like super invested to go and
see Keesa, like, you know,
this is 1 perspective versus that is a
different perspective,
but I do value that.
I have done that in the past,
but I felt that it was just consuming a
lot of my time and energy,
and I felt that...
internal knowledge, like, you know,
it's not really needed. You know,
Yeah.
Mhm.
it was just too much of information.
So I've really limited myself and,
but I used to do that for global news,
not for India, Indian news,
Mm.
because there's anyways a lot of noise
here.
Yeah.
Yeah, that is true. Okay,
what if you want like a balanced view on
a topic? I think when I say news,
immediately it look like, you know,
a lot of political situation comes to our
mind, but say some a topic,
just something cross my head, right?
Like AI, for example,
Mm.
there are like sort of you get to see
both sides of things, you know,
how it's great for humanity and how it's
not.
great for humanity, right? Like so,
and to maintain your sanity,
And...
sometimes that balanced view is required.
So how do you sort of do, first of all,
have you faced that kind of thing?
I'm just giving AI as an example,
but I wanted us to, you know,
maybe think beyond the politics and
political situations.
It could really be anything.
You know,
so how do you sort of try getting a
balanced view of something? Yeah,
that probably, you know,
you are looking at in a day-to-day work.
Yeah.
So.
Again,
I'm not really looking at a very balanced
view. Like, for example,
if there's something new happening in the
world of AI, it's a news to me. Like,
you know, say there is a new model that,
Mm.
like, you know,
you're talking about that Meta has come
up with a new model. So for me, I mean,
there is no right or wrong. It's.
Hmm.
a new technology,
it will have positives and negatives,
Mhm.
right? So in tech created things,
there's no positive or negative for me.
Mm.
I mean, it is as it is,
but say the impact of AI on jobs, right?
There are perspectives where people talk
about it. So I would.
Mm.
try to understand it from an economics
point of view.
So there are certain YouTube channels
that talk from an economic point of view.
Mm.
There are some channels that talk from a
more doomsday context point of view that
know that the world is like probably
going to end and there's a lot of things
happening. But for me,
that is just like story, right?
Mhm.
It's like a narrative because.
Okay.
I'm just consuming as a story.
I don't really ponder over it.
And I would just read it as a like an
I'll just see it as an article.
Mm.
I read it as an article,
but if there's anything,
any development that is important for me
to know, it's more like, okay,
I know that this is happening.
I should just be aware of it and I can
bring that up in my conversations with.
my friends or colleagues.
So then I can have a,
because I'm sure they also do read about
it and then we can have a balanced
Team.
perspective by talking to each other.
OK, alright.
What else?
Anything that you want to point out in
terms of news,
like just your general experience,
how important it is for you?
What do you feel after reading a piece of
news? You know,
do you just like consume the information?
And I know with most cases that happens,
but just want to sort of understand.
I'm sure we don't give it so much thought.
You know,
we just read the news and forget about it.
But if you have anything.
You can share that.
So again, I think news for me,
it's one is just understanding,
just keeping myself updated so there are
no like emotions attached to it.
It's just like read it as is,
understand what is happening.
And obviously there are biases like,
you know, based on the news media, like,
Mm.
you know,
how they want to portray a story.
So anything like any topic,
there will be a political side to it,
right?
Be it like even as simple as the World
Cup, right?
And if you follow this year's World Cup,
like there are people who are saying that
the Argentina is not doing a good job and
there's a lot of backstory behind it,
how the FIFA president wants them to go
to the final.
But you might also see it just as a sport
where a player has played in this
specific way.
So it depends on how the article is
written or how the news is portrayed.
So I think that becomes important.
So for me, I'm just scanning through it,
but if there is specific topic that
interests me,
then I would then deep dive and I would
just try to.
Try to see the opinion also on Reddit
because I think there also people talk
about their perspective.
They do share links which I would have
never like found out about.
But it's not that I will always go to
Mm.
specific channels. I...
I subscribe to different YouTube channels.
I try to keep it a bit neutral so that at
least I'm getting like different
perspectives on it. But yeah,
I think the challenges is that.
Like how much time can you spend?
Like for me, if I have to spend,
I would maximum spend say half an hour in
a day for news.
Okay.
And if the challenge that I'm facing
right now would be my own bias,
that if I am following a specific kind of
news.
Channels, news outlet.
Most of what they're saying probably is
adding,
it's becoming like a confirmation bias
for me in specific topics. So, you know,
you never get to know the other side.
I think that's a good problem that you've
picked.
But I don't know how much value will it
be.
add in certain topics in political topics
or in certain areas,
I think it'll definitely add value.
So if that can be like really compressed
into like something which is more bite
size,
maybe that'll really help me because I
don't want to spend too much time on news.
I want to limit it to like say half an
hour in a day.
and it can give me a good all-round view
of certain topics, then yeah,
Mm.
that would really add value.
Okay. Also,
do you have like specific favourite
topics? Like, again, as I said,
I think we just, we think a lot on this,
when we say news politics, but I think,
I don't know, we may remember as kids,
right?
We all always had a favourite section.
Do you think that still exists? Like you,
there are things, topics that...
really interests you and there are topics
that you like, you know,
don't care about kind of thing.
Um, so...
The funny thing is now news is like news
and media.
I think that the lines for me are
blurring because I also consume a lot on
YouTube and Instagram.
So it's no longer like, you know,
read a paper,
you go to the sports section.
Like as a kid,
I would always go to the sports section,
but now I'm not super interested in
sports section.
Mm.
I would rather learn more about world
politics and technology.
I think those two are my go-to and a bit
of economics.
Okay, fine.
All right.
Economics and business basically stock
market then those so it has changed.
No.
So what I'm trying to get to is that
there are sections that you enjoy a
little more than, like,
I think news sometimes is a lot of gossip
as well these days. Like,
and if you see like one article of it,
Google, for example,
Google News will just show you like every
day it will update you about, you know,
the.
Oh,
she killed this and she said this and
then you know something else the next day
like, you know,
like it just and it is so addictive
sometimes, you know, it's like you,
you know, it's nonsense,
but you keep going back to it. So yeah.
Yeah, those, those are those are the,
you know,
news articles that I avoid because it's
like they'll hype it up and it's going to
Yeah.
Huh?
be like nothing, you know.
Exactly, yeah. It's just drama.
But what I, yeah,
so but what I have also do is like,
so for my stock market and for like these
Bollywood gossip,
Reddit is a better place I feel because
there people talk about it,
they discuss their different channels and
you can just join them and they'll.
Okay.
you'll get more like updates,
but it's not going to be like really
sensationalized.
It'll just be like a very short paragraph,
like 5 minute read, that's it.
And no drama.
Mm.
The writing is also like very like,
you know, people writing.
So you feel that you can trust them
versus people and then mainstream media,
they just want your clicks and your views,
right? So.
Yeah,
so I still go to Reddit for Bollywood
news, which is still interesting.
I'm not saying I'm not interested,
Yeah.
but yeah, I get it.
Okay, so I think Jyotish, as humans,
we all have a certain view around things,
right? Certain perspective.
And we know that most of the news
channels today, we are,
or even Google as a matter of fact, right?
It somewhere knows,
it understands your bias. Would you want,
Ohh.
do you think, would you enjoy a tool?
That challenges your existing views,
or you know,
is probably saying something that doesn't,
you know.
aligned with the bias that you have.
Yeah, yeah, definitely.
I think I definitely need that because
YouTube and my Google,
I think all of that is now completely
like optimised for supporting my
worldview.
And that's what we are just like,
everyone's, I'm just gonna be like, okay,
Mm.
I'm right.
And if that is going to happen,
I'm never going to learn.
So a tool like that will definitely be
really helpful.
Okay.
Because even if I try,
I'm not going to find like, no,
a different view.
So like I sometimes try and read about
certain creators on Reddit and like they
say, okay,
they have a very different view.
Say there's a dam that is getting built.
So there are a lot of environmental
impact, right? People are saying, like,
The.
you know, trees are going to get caught.
There's going to be this problem, but.
You might also want to know why,
how is it going to help, say,
generate more electricity or, you know,
help some other aspects, right?
It.
Help us in some different areas.
So it's always going to be good to have
that.
Okay, good.
All right, so now let me share one.
If there's anything else that you want to
share,
otherwise I'll just share one link with
you. Oh, yeah.
Nothing else, I think we have covered.
I actually,
I have not really thought about this.
Also,
it's interesting how even my consumption
of media has really changed in the past
two years. In fact, winter also was good.
Jha.
Actually, Reddit, you,
I know people and I think people in US
really depend on Reddit for a lot of
things.
Yeah.
I was not sure if it's this popular in
India also.
Yeah.
Yeah, that it is good.
Twitter used to be my go-to place,
but after what Elon Musk has done,
not like Twitter has a lot of like
It.
unverified things.
So I don't like follow Twitter,
Okay, okay.
but Twitter was really good because you
get news very instantly.
If you remember, like a few years back,
like news channels would like, you know,
say, okay,
this has come out on Twitter because
Twitter was faster than other actual news
channels.
So that used to be my go-to place,
but now after Elon Musk,
I think things are being changed.
Okay.
Things are moved to Reddit.
Okay.
All right,
so I have just shared the link with you.
If you can just open it and share your
screen with me.
Okay.
So.
Yeah,
so I think the UI piece and navigation
and all that is not that important,
but from the concept perspective,
Mm.
if you have any thoughts, you can,
you know, share that with me.
Okay, so today's topic, so I see the date,
perspective radar.
So, today's topics, all topics, business,
if types.
It's been playing.
So it says, OK.
On topics, business technology,
I'm just like going through what all is
covered, see, go into this.
Let's see.
Individual problems.
So, multiple perspective, basically,
is this like segments that will get
impacted, like, or like perspective?
Yeah, yeah,
looks like I did not create this is
created by Diya,
but it seems like that on the specific
Okay.
news, what would be the economic thing,
what will be the thing on government,
Good.
so yeah.
Yes, we do.
Make publications.
So.
I think this is curated well,
a couple of like observations. Again,
I have stopped consuming news.
on laptops or on computers.
It's mostly on phone. So for me,
Hmm.
I'm seeing this after a long time.
I'm bringing back memories of seeing this
like, no,
when I go to maybe 10 years back,
I would go to bbc.
com and see the thing or go to NGTV and
Yeah.
see the news.
Um...
But now mostly it's on phone.
So the thing is with phone,
Yeah.
I'm seeing one thing at a time.
Like so now this is this feels very
intimidating to me because again,
it's been a while, right?
Mhm.
Yeah.
So I don't know what to see. I mean,
I'll definitely sort this with maybe if
there was a headline that could be like
helpful and.
Maybe I'm assuming this will also like
get curated basis what I prefer,
but if I see business or technology.
There's a lot, right? I mean,
let's say business would have like a
couple of things. So this is developing.
Um, this it now makes this this minute we.
And.
One thing that is missing I feel is like
images,
maybe like the hierarchy because
everything is at the same level right now.
Mm.
Like how we have a first,
like within a first page also we have a
hero story, right?
A big story and we used to have then
Yeah.
smaller cutouts, right?
And even if you see that representation
Yeah, yeah.
on.
on our laptop on the website,
there's to be like some big stories with
like big images and then there would be
like smaller ones. So visually,
like again,
maybe that is a generation that I come
from.
Maybe someone who's not seen that will be
okay. But for me, maybe that is like.
Help make making it a little difficult
for me to, like, decide what to pick, um,
like, like, where, what,
what is my eye movement right now?
That's that's I'm finding that a little
tricky, um, and...
There is a lot of detail.
Like if I go to this space,
for someone like me, maybe, like,
you know,
Mm.
if I have to go through it again,
this is what I was saying.
Like there's so much detailed analysis,
like finishing one news and then going to
Mm.
the next one itself gets very tiring.
Yeah.
for me and that's why I stopped doing it
and I was really into it. Like I said,
I was going to take this as my thesis,
but like I after a point I was like,
Yeah.
and maybe like if you give me just this,
this much like this first level pay,
very like high level bullet points,
I think that.
I'm, I'm,
I'll be more than happy with that, and...
Yeah,
I think you're giving just too much
information in the name of showing the
sources and this and that. Yeah.
Yeah, you can, you can maybe if you want,
you can like, you know, call for it,
like maybe not have it upfront.
I don't know, but for me, if I want,
I would then see, okay,
do I really need to trust?
I will then see the sources.
Like say story also like this.
I've seen this pattern when there's a
cricket match or if there is a developing
story, that is where you see this, right?
Okay, like this happened,
then this happened, then this happened.
It.
When I like say story in 60 seconds,
I would now compare it to like a short
Mm.
paragraph which has a 60 second reading
time versus reading it this way. But yeah,
He.
that's my take. So one high level,
give me like a high level picture of this.
And if I want detail,
then show me all of these details that
you have. Because there is value to it.
Just that if I go through all of it,
maybe then it might get really tiring.
Yeah, the news is going to get lost.
It's more for perspectives than, you know,
like, okay,
there is a specific topic and it may not
be a topic of today. It may be a topic of,
say, Dark Ages, right?
Dark Ages was pretty dark,
but just giving an example, right?
Ohh.
So a perspective,
what are the different perspectives on
Dark Ages? So I think that might be a...
just now that we are talking.
It might not be a news thing,
Mm.
but rather perspectives on different
events in history all put together in one
place. For something like that,
this might be a good thing.
And I think we could also bring in like,
and if you are interested, for example,
okay, what was the economic,
what was the impact or, you know,
on macroeconomics of
at that point because of this event.
So then, you know,
And.
it could provide you an answer
accordingly.
So I think some of these things probably
could be there, but you're right,
like just for the sake of consuming the
news, all this might be like too much.
Yeah.
Yeah, this is really good for deep diving.
Like,
Hmm.
say any recent news that I've heard that
in Greater Nicobar and this island,
they were planning to set up a data
center.
Huh, okay.
Now, that is a that is a new topic, right?
And there'll be different stories,
but for me,
the news is they under Nicobar,
there's a data center. Now,
this is what the government has said,
Hmm.
this is the timeline that they're saying,
and that's it.
If I want to understand more perspectives,
what is the impact on the ecology?
Why have they done it? Like, you know,
what is the what are the pros and cons of
Mm.
doing it? Then I can do a deep dive,
definitely.
Yeah, Okay.
And one more thing, again,
for someone like me who consumes a lot of
All right, yeah.
like video and those kind of media,
maybe even links to,
Mm.
I don't know if it's already there,
but maybe even links to social media
Providing the links. Yeah,
because more people,
because, yeah, some social media.
more and more people are depending on.
Jyotish, I have someone on the door,
Yeah.
but I think we are more or less done.
If you have any more things,
Okay.
Sure, sure, I'll do that. OK, I'm sorry.
please message me. Okay. Yeah. All right.
Thank you. Bye.
Bye.